[music]
>> But, before you introduce yourself when
we get into the topic of the CIA and
it's anatomy, is it the case demon where
we're trying to dissect here? Yes.
>> Yes, very good. And I think we will.
>> Yeah.
>> So, so please
John, tell us your story. I think most
people have heard most lot of your
story, but if you can focus on your way
into the CIA, how you were recruited,
your career in the CIA, and what you
think is of
uh
public interest, especially about your
journey.
>> The way that I
was recruited into the CIA is now
illegal.
Um it's been illegal since 1993, but in
the late 1980s,
I was in graduate school at George
Washington University in Washington,
D.C. And I was taking a class called the
psychology of leadership. As part of
this class,
my professor assigned us a paper where
we had to
shadow or follow our bosses for a week
and then write a detailed psychological
profile of our boss.
I worked at a labor union at the time
called the United Food and Commercial
Workers Union.
And I worked for a man that I was
actually a little afraid of. He was a
mean,
angry, racist,
old-school
union organizer.
And in the middle of that week, we got
into an argument and I called him a a
racist, which he was.
And he got so angry that he balled up
his fists, and he set a stance, and I I
put up my hands. I remember thinking, "I
I went too far this time."
I put up my hands, and he says to me,
"My penis is bigger than yours."
And I said, "What?"
And he said, "My penis is bigger than
yours."
And I said, "You know what? You are
insane, and I quit." And I walked out.
And I went back to my apartment, and I
typed my paper, and I said, "He's a
psychopath with psychopathic and violent
tendencies."
So, I sent the paper to the professor.
And a week later, he sent the paper
back, and he gave me an A, and he wrote
in the in the margin, "Please see me
after class."
So, I waited till the class was over,
and I went up to him, and I said, "Dr.
Post, you wanted to see me after class."
And he said, "Come with me to my
office." So, we went to the office, and
he closed the door, and he said,
"Listen,
I'm not really a professor here. I'm a
CIA officer undercover as a professor
here, and I'm looking for people who I
think would fit into the CIA's culture.
I think you would fit into the CIA's
culture.
Do you want to be a CIA officer?"
The truth was, I was getting married in
6 weeks, and I didn't have a job.
So, I said,
"Sure.
>> [laughter]
>> Why not?
I wanted to see the world. I wanted to
do something in public service. I
thought I would probably end up in the
State Department at some point or on
Capitol Hill, but I said, "Sure."
And so,
I went through a series of tests. He
made the right introductions for me. I
had to pass the tests on my own.
And um
and then, a year later I found myself in
the CIA.
I was actually assigned to the office
that he had created called the political
psychology division. He liked that paper
so much that they made me Saddam
Hussein's classified psychologist.
And that's what I did for the next uh
what, 4 years.
>> And then when was this?
>> Uh I I started I was offered the job in
1989. I started the 1st of January 1990.
>> Okay.
>> I see and this was in what's called the
Directorate of Intelligence. It was the
analytic uh wing.
And the funny thing is, and this is in
answer to your question really, why my
career moved so quickly
at least at the beginning.
Um
I was assigned to Iraq
because nothing This is not my words,
this is the office director's words.
Nothing ever happens there.
Nothing. It was the same cabinet since
the 1968 revolution.
And the the exact words were, "Work
hard,
learn the writing tradecraft, and then
you can transfer onto something
interesting like Romania."
>> Well, something really interesting
>> me.
>> Something really interesting happened in
Iraq in 1990.
>> Just as I thought that I knew what I was
talking about. And I really did. I
worked hard. Iraq invaded Kuwait.
And so the morning of August 2nd, 1990,
I walked into the office 6:00 in the
morning and my boss said, "Don't take
your jacket off. We're going to the
White House." I had never been to the
White House before except as a tourist.
And so
we drove to the White House. There was a
Marine waiting for us. He walked us
right into the Oval Office and I'm 25
years old and I'm there with the
president, the vice president, the
national security advisor, the CIA
director,
my boss and me.
And
the president at the time was George
H.W. Bush, the father.
And um we walked in. He was very upset.
And he finally said, "Gentlemen, please
sit down. Sit down." So we sat down.
And he looks around and he says, "Well,
now what do I do?"
And everybody turned and looked at me.
And I looked at him. And we're just
looking at each other.
And then I said, "Oh, well, uh as you
know, Mr. President,
Iraqi troops crossed the Kuwaiti border
at 2:00 this morning. The
ruling ruling family has fled to Saudi
Arabia, etc., etc."
And I became the go-to person
for Saddam Hussein's state of mind
and how to
pressure him
and exploit the pressure on him.
>> [clears throat]
>> So what So what's uh psychological
weaknesses have you found?
>> Um Saddam
There's There's a bad habit that
American leaders have, and that is
calling people with whom they disagree
crazy.
"Oh, those ayatollahs, they're crazy."
No, they're not crazy. They don't like
you.
>> [clears throat]
>> That doesn't mean they're crazy.
With Saddam,
I felt like I made a breakthrough in our
analysis when I said, "Saddam is not
crazy. He's not even angry.
He's a mob boss.
He runs the country the way a New York
City Mafia Don would run a family.
And so if we
anticipate his behavior
akin to how we would anticipate the
behavior of, you know, Don Corleone,
I think we can figure out what the man
intends to do.
Every once in a while he would do
something that we would deem crazy. If
you spoke out against him, this is at
the very end of his rule. Um
he would have your tongue cut out
[clears throat] and nailed to the front
door of your house.
So, nobody else in the neighborhood says
anything about Saddam Hussein.
I did that for
the next uh
3 years. So, almost 4 years I I was on
Iraq. And um
I really wanted to go overseas.
So, I applied for a position with the
State Department. It's a rotation from
the CIA to the State Department. That um
sent me to Arabic language training for
a full year. I have a facility for
languages, so I I had a good experience
with Arabic. And then I went to Bahrain
for 2 years as the economic officer. And
then back to headquarters on Iraq.
By 1997,
this is very boring.
Uh Saddam is not going anywhere by 1997.
And um
I decided to do something completely
different. And I saw a job opening for
uh an operations officer
on counterterrorism in Athens.
I had zero experience in operations.
Nothing.
And back then, operations was over here
and analysis over here, and the two
never met.
It's different now.
But, I went to see the the hiring
authority and I said, "Listen, I don't
have any operational experience at all,
but I speak fluent Greek and Arabic."
And he said, "Really? Are you willing to
be tested?" And I said, "Sure, I just
tested recently, but I'll test again if
you want me to."
And I did, and I tested fluent, and I
got the job. So, I went through all the
operational training, and it is
extensive.
>> [clears throat]
>> Everything from how to recruit a spy to
steal a secret
to weapons and explosives and
surveillance and crashing through
roadblocks. I had to have my knees
replaced because they don't give you
nice cars to crash. They give you trash
cars to crash. And so, when you crash
through the roadblock,
the seat comes detached, and I broke
both of my knees on the dashboard.
So, now I have titanium knees.
Yeah.
Thanks. And nobody have even said, "Hey,
sorry about your knees." Nothing.
Anyway, I found that I had a knack for
it, and so operations were for me.
>> And uh
then
9/11 happened.
>> Yeah. I got back from Athens in the
summer of 2000 only because
there was a group there that tried to
assassinate me.
Um so, I got back to headquarters,
and I was working on um
in the counterterrorism center.
And then 9/11 happened.
And uh I was sent to Pakistan as the
chief of counterterrorism operations.
>> Okay. Um and as I understand it, was was
it Cofer Black that sent you there?
>> Yes. Cofer Black.
>> Yeah.
>> He became quite uh notorious.
>> Can you tell us about Cofer Black?
>> Cofer was a
>> um
>> career-long CIA officer. He had been
station chief in multiple, many places.
He made a name for himself at the CIA by
capturing Carlos the Jackal. If I I
think we're all old enough to remember
Carlos the Jackal. I teach a class now
at the University of Salamanca in Spain,
and none of those kids have ever heard
of Carlos the Jackal.
None of those kids really even could
pick out Osama bin Laden in a picture.
But uh they're all born after 9/11. And
in my mind, 9/11 was, you know, 2 weeks
ago.
So, Cofer made a name for himself by
leading the capture of Carlos the
Jackal,
rose to become the director of
counterterrorism,
briefly became
Ambassador Cofer Black, the special
coordinator for counterterrorism at the
State Department, but then he resigned
and went to Blackwater and became the
finally the chairman
of Blackwater. And they did some very,
very ugly things.
>> Yeah, he he he's got kind of a strange
story going. Like in the epicenter where
really strange things happens. And he's
always in Afghanistan and and the
Ukraine war, he was sitting in the board
of of Burisma.
>> Yep, he was.
>> Yeah.
>> [snorts]
>> Yeah, the funny thing about Cofer and a
lot of those
those men, and they're all men at the
senior-most level, is
once they make the senior intelligence
service, they begin to realize just how
much money is out there
that's there's for the taking.
All they have to do is retire.
And then they find themselves on the
board of Burisma or on the board of
Palantir or Nvidia or, you meta or, you
know, anything. And they're making
millions and millions of dollars. George
Tenet went to a
venture capital firm, and he makes more
money than he could count in a lifetime.
>> Yeah.
>> And he was just a career public servant.
I make more than George ever made at the
CIA.
>> Yeah.
>> And I don't make very much.
>> And then so 9/11 happened and you went
to Pakistan and you were involved with
Al-Qaeda and all that stuff.
Uh
but then uh
something happened and uh you got into
trouble.
>> Yes.
Which believe me, I would gladly do it
again today if I had the opportunity.
People say all the time, you don't show
any remorse. No,
I don't. I'm not sorry for what I did.
When I got back from Pakistan in May of
2002,
I was approached by a senior officer in
the Counterterrorism Center and he asked
me if I wanted to be, his words,
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques. I had never
heard that term before. I said, what
does that mean?
And he said, we're going to start
getting rough with these guys.
And I said,
what does that mean?
And then he listed these 10
techniques that they were going to start
using. And I said, that sounds like a
torture program.
And he said, it's not a torture program.
The the Justice Department approved it
and the president signed it. I said,
let me think about it for an hour.
I walked out of the cafeteria
and I went up to the seventh floor of
the CIA, the executive floor.
And there were there's a very very
senior CIA officer up there for whom I
had worked in the Middle East 10 years
earlier.
And
and I knocked on his door and I said,
sorry to bother you,
but I was just asked if I wanted to be
certified in these enhanced
interrogation techniques. What do you
think of that?
And he said, first let's call a spade a
spade. This is a torture program.
They can call it whatever they want, but
it's a torture program. And torture is a
slippery slope. He said, you know how
these guys are. They're cowboys.
And somebody's going to go too far and
they're going to kill a prisoner.
And when that happens, there's going to
be a congressional investigation and
then there's going to be
a Justice Department investigation and
somebody's he's to go to prison. Do you
want to go to prison? And I said, "No, I
don't want to go to prison." As I said
the other day, I was the only one who
went to prison.
But I said, "No, no, I don't want to go
to prison." I went back downstairs. I
found that colleague, and I said, "This
is a torture program. I have a moral and
ethical problem with it. I think it's
illegal
on top of it,
and I don't want to have anything to do
with it." As an aside,
my promotion panel met a week later, and
I was passed over for promotion. I had
just returned from Pakistan,
where I captured with these hands,
I'm not allowed to say the number of
Al-Qaeda prisoners, but it was the
[clears throat] most It was the biggest
counterterrorism capture in the history
of the CIA,
including Abu Zubaydah, who we believed
was the number three in Al-Qaeda at the
time. I got passed over for promotion.
And the man who replaced Cofer,
a
>> [clears throat]
>> dark, notorious officer named Jose
Rodriguez.
Um Jose said that I had demonstrated a
shocking lack of commitment to
counterterrorism because I wouldn't be
trained in this torture program.
I didn't care.
The uh the officer that I went to talk
to that day, he promoted me with
a stroke of his pen.
But he said, "You know, you're you're
senior enough now where
this position you've taken, it's going
to hurt you."
And I said, "I don't care."
>> But you got into problem when you were
interviewed.
>> The The big problem came later. The The
I was I was called behind my back the
human rights guy.
And um one of my colleagues said, "You
know, they talk about you behind your
back. They call you the human rights
guy." And I said, "Yeah, I know. I've
heard that." He said, "You know, that's
not a compliment."
And I said, "I know. I don't care." I
said, "I'm right and they're wrong and
it's just as simple as that. So, I left
the CIA in 2004. I went into the private
sector.
And then in 2007, December,
uh I got a call from a very important,
prominent American journalist, Brian
Ross from ABC News.
And he said that he had a source who
said that I had tortured Abu Zubaydah. I
said, it's absolutely not true. I was
the only person who was kind to Abu
Zubaydah.
And he said, well, you're welcome to
come on the show and defend yourself.
I didn't know that that was a reporter's
trick
because I had never met a reporter
before. I was a CIA undercover officer.
I'm not going to meet with reporters.
And so, um
I said, I'll think about it.
That week, that was on a Monday,
on Wednesday, President George W. Bush
gave a press conference in which
he looked right in the camera and he
went like this.
We do not torture.
And I said to my wife, she was a senior
CIA officer, too. I said, he's a
bald-faced liar. He's looking the
American people in the eye and he's just
lying right to our faces.
And then 2 days later, it was Friday,
he was walking out of the back, that
it's called the South Portico of the
White House to get on the helicopter to
go to Camp David for the weekend. And a
reporter shouted a question about
torture. And he stopped and he said,
well, if there is torture,
it's because of a rogue CIA officer.
And I said to my wife, Brian Ross's
source is at the White House and they're
going to pin this on me.
So, I called him and I said, I'll give
you your interview. And I decided in the
days leading up to that interview that
whatever he asked me, I was simply going
to tell the truth.
And then just let the cards fall. I
believed that that program was illegal,
that it just
>> And you were right. You had the whole
world on your side and they framed you
later on. Yeah?
>> They did.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. But, you know what?
My my now ex-wife
um
gave me some very good advice and she
said, "You have to keep telling your
story
over and over again because eventually
they're going to move on to their next
victim." And they did. It was at
Snowden.
And she said, "If you keep talking about
this, your side of the story will be the
side of record
and nobody will remember what their side
of the story was."
And she was right.
>> [snorts]
>> And now
thanks to John McCain and Dianne
Feinstein,
uh torture is illegal in the United
States. It's punishable by 20 years in
prison. And in fact,
6 weeks before I was released from
prison,
um I was I was allowed to call my wife
every other day for 15 minutes. So, I
called her 6 weeks before I left and um
and I said, "How was your day?" She
said, "It was great." I said, "Really?
Why was it great?"
And she said, "Because the Senate
torture report came out today and it
proved that everything you said was
true."
And John McCain,
God bless him, John McCain and I
disagreed on 99% of the issues.
But, he stood on the floor of the Senate
that day and he he said that the that
the country owed me a debt of thanks
because if I had not told the American
people what the CIA was doing in their
name,
they would never have known that the
George W. Bush
regime was a terrorist regime.
John John McCain was really a lovely
man.
Like I say, we disagreed on 99% of the
issues, but his office was next door to
John Kerry's office, and I was John
Kerry's um intelligence adviser, and I
was the senior investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee from
2009 to the middle of 2011. And their
offices were next door to each other.
So, when there would be a vote, I would
walk out with Kerry, and invariably we
would see McCain, and McCain would
always come over to shake my hand. And
he would always say, "How are you today,
John?" And I'd say, "I'm doing great,
Senator. Thank you. How are you doing?"
"I'm doing great."
And then finally Kerry said one day,
"Why don't you and McCain get a hotel
room?"
And I said, "You know, I said this this
is like a serious thing. It's not It's
not funny games for him. It was because
he was tortured for 7 years. He knows
what this is like."
And he respected me. And then when I got
out of prison, the week I got out of
prison, I think I'd been home about 4
days,
his legislative director called me and
said, "Senator McCain says welcome home,
and he wants to know what he can do to
be helpful."
And I said, "These damn Obama people,
they took my pension. I'm going to have
to work until the day I die."
And so McCain worked to get my pension
back. I'm sorry to say that he got sick.
He got brain cancer and and died before
we could do it, but
but there was no way that I could help
John McCain.
He was only helping me because he was a
good man.
>> Okay, but but let's get to to the CIA
now. So, while we have some time,
>> Yes.
>> could you just lay out what what what is
the CIA? You were talking about you got
the analytics department and you got the
operations department. I been listening
to Ray McGovern.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I I know that Yeah, I know it was
built that way to keep the the
operational part from
independent
so they won't influence the analytics
part.
>> It was so so
uh specific that we used to wear these
badges. You have a blue badge with your
picture on it and [snorts] a letter H.
A letter H says you have top secret
special [snorts] intelligence special
compartmented compartmented information
um
talent keyhole gamma clearance. The
highest clearance in government.
But you were not allowed on the sixth
floor
because that's where the operations
directorate was and they had HR
on their badge.
Which meant they had all those
clearances, too, but they also had
operational clearances that you were not
allowed to know about. Now, since 9/11,
everybody just sits in one giant room
and reads everything, but it was very
very different back then. And and in
addition, there was also a directorate
of science and technology
and a directorate of administration, the
paper pushers, and then besides that
there was an independent group
um
called the office of the director that
included security, medical
you know, these guys
all the extra people that don't quite
fit in
in the other directorates.
>> If if you look at the like what the CIA
does, the the operational part
uh [clears throat]
>> It's actually quite so
>> Kennedy's uh chief of special operations
uh Fletcher Prouty, he wrote a very
interesting book.
Uh
The Secret Team.
>> Mhm.
>> [clears throat]
>> And he he's he's
uh he describes a system as functioning
like you got this secret team that's
like
an elite
performance
team that traveled the world and do
different covert operations, false
flags, and stuff like that to
sort of massage reality and create a
narrative like Karl Rove. He spoke about
now we're an empire, we create reality
and you are left to study it and when
you've studied we have already created a
new reality that you can study.
>> Yeah.
>> So it paints a picture that you got the
covert part sort of tricking the
intelligence part,
making up stories like the Northwood uh
Operation Northwood.
>> Mhm.
>> What do you think about that idea? I
think that's true.
>> Yeah.
>> And this is that's a pretty scary
picture, right? Because
>> And we're back at that again. Yeah.
There was this period
Well, the CIA was founded in 1947 with
passage of the National Security Act of
1947. It also created the National
Security Council.
And
>> With a little loophole in that.
>> Absolutely right. And then in 1949 the
CIA
uh
carried out its first covert action
program.
It
stole the Italian elections.
And it did that in a very
unsophisticated way.
Um [snorts] it bribed journalists with
$150,000
to write pro
um
conservative
Christian Democratic Party articles and
to write anti-communist articles. The
communists were ahead in the polls, the
CIA spent this money and recruited all
these journalists, and the Christian
Democrats won the election. That was the
first
first one.
>> [snorts]
>> Five short years later, the CIA is
overthrowing governments in the
Dominican Republic, in Guatemala, in
Cyprus, and all over the world.
Without any plan for what comes next.
That was the policy makers problem.
The CIA's job was just go in there
>> Just just get rid rid of the communists
or left wing.
>> Patrice Lumumba, for example, wipe out
the communists, and then just let the
State Department figure out what happens
next.
>> Because this this tour you're you're
making, it's the headline is all about
how do we avoid the Third World War? How
do we
get peace?
I mean, you study the history of of all
these covert operations, and you have
CIA like a short for I mean, it's
military intelligence. You've got the
NSA,
all of these different
organizations working
in a in a way that's not really
in line with with peace. So, so what
what what what should people understand
how this work? On what different fronts
does it work? You talk about the media,
and and what's more? Could you just give
the different different fronts?
>> This is something that almost nobody
understands, including most Americans.
The CIA is not a policy organization.
The CIA is a policy support
organization.
So, these orders, overthrow this
government, assassinate this leader,
these come from the White House.
It's the White House that makes these
decisions.
The president, the national security
advisor. Sometimes they'll bring in the
secretaries of state and defense.
Sometimes.
But, these orders come from the White
House, and this is why this is such a
big problem.
Because it's not specifically tied to a
Republican or to a Democrat. They're all
criminals. Sometimes
>> they come with sort of suggestions,
shouldn't we do this? And the president
says, "No." Like the Northwood
operations.
>> Yes. And then something funny might
happen to the president.
>> And this is exactly Yes, that's
important. And this is exactly why
This is exactly why
>> A military Well, that's tragic, I would
say.
>> Yeah, certainly. And we could talk about
that. But, this is why a military
officer should never be the CIA
director.
Because military officers became
generals or admirals by saying, "Yes,
sir."
And you don't want a
a CIA director
to say, "Yes, sir." You want a CIA
director to say, "Mr. President, that's
a terrible idea."
>> Have you got Have you got an example of
a good CIA director?
>> John McCone.
>> Okay.
>> And I'll tell you the honest-to-God's
truth, I can't think of another one.
Maybe Stansfield Turner. So, John McCone
was the CIA director under John F.
Kennedy.
And Stansfield Turner was the CIA
director under
Jimmy Carter.
And they are both considered to be in
the CIA
fail directors.
Because they tried to rein the
organization in. And I'll give you an
example. Robert F. Kennedy Jr. is a
friend of mine. Please don't judge me
for that.
>> [laughter]
>> Um
He told me
>> a looting good.
>> He's trying.
>> Yeah, sure. He's trying.
>> But, then he says, "Oh, I have a a worm
in my brain. It's like, "Stop."
"Oh, I I found a dead bear in the road
and I put him in the trunk of my car."
Stop. Why do you say these things?
Anyway, that's a
different story.
So, he told me a story one time
that I've been thinking about ever
since.
He said on the day that his uncle was
killed, John John Kennedy,
his mother
Bobby's mother went to pick him up at
school
20 minutes after the assassination.
And when he came back, they pulled into
the driveway
and his father,
Robert Kennedy Sr., was standing there
with Director McCone. Now, the McCones
were very very close friends with the
Kennedys, with all the Kennedys. Mrs.
McCone had died of breast cancer 6
months earlier
and the Kennedys were afraid
that Director McCone was so depressed
that he might take his own life.
So, they invited him to dinner seven
nights a week and after dinner he and
Bobby Kennedy would swim in the pool.
When
Bobby Jr. pulls in with his mother,
gets out of the car, he heard his father
say
to McCone, "Tell me your people didn't
do this."
And McCone said,
"I don't know who did it."
He did not say,
"Of course my people didn't do it. Are
you crazy?"
>> That kind of fits in with Fletcher
Prouty's uh um
>> Yes.
>> very much description of the whole
workings of it.
>> Yes.
>> And he's Mr. X in in
Oliver Stone's JFK.
Yeah.
>> So, there might have been the secret
team that did that operation.
>> I think there probably was.
>> Yeah, but but back to how this system
works. What what what different fronts
do they work on apart from media or or
>> It is so much more complicated now
because [clears throat] when when I was
there,
we were just starting to think about
technology.
And now, they're up to their chins
in
well, Palantir. The CIA created
Palantir.
In the immediate aftermath of 9/11,
George Tenet, who was the CIA director
at the time, went to Capitol Hill and
said, "We want special permission, a
legal waiver, to invest in tech
companies."
That is crazy.
There's not supposed to be any
connection between the private sector
and the CIA.
But he got his waiver. In defense of the
free market, right? In defense of the
free market. That's the American way,
>> Yes, that's of course.
>> So, the CIA invested $15 million
in Palantir to get them started. As soon
as the CIA committed money,
everybody else jumped in.
And now, the CIA owns something like 40%
of Palantir.
>> So, you think we should be worried here
in Sweden about Palantir?
>> I would be very worried about Palantir,
yes.
>> When our prime minister meets Palantir
and makes contracts and stuff like that.
>> When you know, when I when I heard that
the other day for the first time, it
made the hair on the back of my neck
stand up.
>> Well, come to the club.
>> Wow.
And it's not just Palantir. We used to
we used to kind of joke around. People
would say, "Oh, is it cool you have so
many gadgets?" And I'd say, "Actually,
we buy most of those gadgets on Amazon."
We do. Because it doesn't you why would
you spend a million dollars making a
gadget from scratch when you can just
buy it on Amazon for $100?
My first day at the CIA,
um my boss was taking me around the
building to give me a tour. And there's
a uh
there's a grassy area. The the the
building is a square, and in the center
is a grassy area that nobody has access
to.
And I looked out the window, and there
was a robot cutting the grass. And I
said, "Oh my gosh, that there's a robot
out there cutting the grass."
And he said, "Yeah, you know, we we
invent a lot of things, and then we just
can't figure out an operational use for
them. So,
we made this one cut the grass.
Five years later,
I see the Roomba advertised on
television, and I said, "That's the
robot I saw cutting the grass at the
CIA." Now, everybody has them. They're
$150 on Amazon.
So, it's different now. It's more
it's more dangerous now. It's more of a
threat to our civil liberties now than
it was 20 or 25 years ago. I'm I'm
deeply worried about it. Can I back up a
little bit, too? So, in in the in the
purest sense, the job of the CIA, very
simply, is to recruit spies to steal
secrets,
and to analyze those secrets so that the
policy maker can make the best informed
policy.
In a perfect world, that's what they do.
>> The official story.
>> That's the official story, yeah.
Really, what they do is
anything they want to do.
Anything. If they don't like your face,
they might just blow it off.
Or they don't like the sermons that
you're giving, they're going to kidnap
you and send you to Egypt, and by God,
you're never going to give a sermon like
that again, if you make it out alive.
Um so, it's it's different now. Even
Barack Obama
>> What what most is done on like country
level is is managing populations, like
the battle for the hearts and minds of
>> That's a part of it. There's There's one
one division at the CIA that does things
like that. It's called active measures.
It's It's propaganda. It's controlling
the news media. It's controlling the
national debate on XYZ issue.
>> So, how often when you watch the news,
do you think, "Oh, that that comes from
from that section?"
>> Every day.
I don't I I can't watch the American
news anymore. People ask me all the
time, "Where do you get your news?"
And my answer is I get it from
everywhere.
Because you can't trust it anybody.
So, I start off you have you have to
know what everybody's saying. So, I
start off with The New York Times, The
Washington Post, The Wall Street
Journal, the Los Angeles Times.
And then I go to
CNN, Fox, MSNBC. That's the
establishment, the the pro-CIA media.
>> And when you want to get the real stuff?
>> Then I go to Grayzone, I go to Covert
Action Magazine, I go to um
>> Consortium News.
>> Consortium News, I'm on the board of
Consortium News, which I forgot to
mention Consortium News. Uh
reader-supported news, then I go to Al
Jazeera and the Al-Monitor and Middle
East Eye and uh Electronic Intifada.
>> We put in all the links in the video
later.
>> They're excellent. They're really
excellent. Especially especially um
uh
the Grayzone.
Uh they do incredible for for the the
minuscule budget that they have.
And and the
small number of of people, they break
major stories.
And you know that they're on the right
track because that the government will
call them Russian stooges,
>> [snorts]
>> you know, or conspiracy theorists.
>> This is a good indication when where you
can find this out.
>> That's exactly right.
Yeah. As much as I hate The Intercept
and I genuinely have hatred in my heart
for the Intercept. They actually do some
good reporting.
>> It was good when Green
Glenn Green worked there.
>> No, it wasn't.
>> Oh, okay.
>> No, they outed five whistleblowers, and
all five of us went to prison.
>> Oh, really?
>> I tweeted at Glenn. Glenn and I went to
college together, and we really don't
like each other very much.
And I tweeted at at
at Glenn when I got out of prison, and I
said, "Glenn,
are you guys undercover FBI agents, or
are you just stupid?"
>> [laughter]
>> Because no reporter who calls himself a
national security journalist
outs five national security
whistleblowers and sends them all to
prison.
But the Intercept did.